Finding aid to Gloria W. Heath papers CA.MS.00304
Smith College Archives
Gloria W. Heath papers
1941-2012
Smith College Archives
Heath, Gloria W.
CA.MS.00304
2.5 linear feet (7 containers)
2.708 linear feet (8 containers)
The Gloria W. Heath papers contain biographical information, correspondence, professional files, and publications of Gloria W. Heath, Class of 1943.
Biographical / Historical
Gloria Whitton Heath graduated from Smith College in 1943, majoring in Education. During the spring of 1941, Heath fell in love with flying, motivating her, along with 14 other students, to pool their money together to buy a plane, christened the "Bird of Paradise" and painted with the class colors. The group took lessons and Heath obtained her private pilot's license. During World War II, Heath flew with the Women Airforce Service Pilots (WASPs), the first group of American women to fly military aircraft, earning the rank of second lieutenant. After the war, Heath became an expert in the field of search and rescue. She worked in the insurance field, founded the Flight Safety Foundation, and consulted with NASA.
Heath has earned several awards. She was given the Laura Tabor Barbour Air Safety Award in 1965 and received the Smith College Medal in 1971. In 2009, Heath was among the 300 women WASPs to receive the Congressional Gold Medal, the highest civilian award given by Congress, by President Barack Obama and the United States Congress.
Scope and Contents
The materials in the Gloria W. Heath papers document Heath's career in aerospace, her work as a WASP during World War II, and her connection to Smith College.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into six series:
Series I: Biographical Material
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Professional Employment
Series IV: Professional Societies
Series V: Awards
Series VI: Publications
Conditions Governing Access
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated to the Smith College Archives by Gloria W. Heath.
Smith College - Alumni and alumnae - History - Sources; Heath, Gloria W.
- Series I: Biographical Material
  - Index and Description of Consultant Activities, 1965-1973 (Box 112)
  - Biographical Material, 1941-1982; undated (Box 112)
  - Smith College Flying Club, 1941-1943 (Box 112)
  - Miscellaneous, 1961-2009; undated (Box 112)
  - Photographs, 1963; undated (Box 112)
  - Photographs - Smith College Flying Club, 1941-1942; undated (Box 112)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - General, 1965-1983; undated (Box 112)
  - Barbour, Clifford E., 1971-1972 (Box 112)
  - Boeing Aerospace Company, 1982 (Box 112)
  - Campbell, Paul A., 1969-1977 (Box 112)
  - Diederiks-Verschoor, 1976-1979 (Box 112)
  - Draper, C. Stark, 1975-1982 (Box 112)
  - Enders, John H., 1978; 1982; undated (Box 112)
  - Fuchs, Heinz S., 1979; 1981 (Box 112)
  - Gazenko, Oleg, 1969-1983 (Box 112)
  - Hinton, Carmelita, 1974; 1983; undated (Box 112)
  - Houze, Robert A., 1973; 1980 (Box 112)
  - McCauley, Jack C., 1969 (Box 112)
  - Morrison, W. S., 1982 (Box 112)
  - Murdock, Mary-Elizabeth, 1972-1983; undated (Box 112)
  - Perry, Geoff, 1975 (Box 112)
  - Prince of the Netherlands, 1969 (Box 112)
  - Reed, John H., 1973; 1975 (Box 112)
  - Saiki, Hisashi, 1980 (Box 112)
  - Space Rescue and Safety Studies Committee, 1979-1983 (Box 112)
  - Stapp, John P., 1974-1975 (Box 112)
  - Stuhlinger, Ernst, 1973- 1979 (Box 112)
  - Publications, 1969-1970; 1973 (Box 112)
- Series III: Professional Employment
  - Daniel and Florence Guggenheim Aviation Safety Center at Cornell University, 1953-1973; undated (Box 113)
  - Flight Safety Foundation, 1955-1970 (Box 113)
  - Flight Safety Foundation, 1970-1983; undated (Box 113)
  - Notes for Course Taught at Connecticut College, 1945 (Box 113)
  - NSTA-NASA Space Shuttle Student Involvement Project, 1983 (Box 113)
  - SAR-ASSIST, Inc. - General, 1962-1968 (Box 113)
  - SAR-ASSIST, Inc. - General, 1970-1977 (Box 114)
  - SAR-ASSIST, Inc. - Atlantic International Air and Surface Search and Rescue Seminar, 1975 (Box 114)
  - SAR-ASSIST, Inc. - CD-10 Proposal, 1973-1978 (Box 114)
  - SAR-ASSIST, Inc. - Harvard Seminar in Aviation and Health Safety, related materials, 1968-1973 (Box 114)
  - SAR-ASSIST, Inc. - International Air Safety Seminar, 1972 (Box 114)
  - SAR-ASSIST, Inc. - Mine Safety, 1969-1970 (Box 114)
  - SAR-ASSIST, Inc. - Space Rescue and Response System, 1969-1976 (Box 114)
  - SAR-ASSIST, Inc. - Assist Texas Instruments Study, 1969-1970 (Box 114)
  - Second World Congress on Emergency and Disaster Medicine, 1981 (Box 114)
  - United Nations Outer Space Conference (UNISPACE 82), 1979-1982 (Box 114)
  - WASPS, 1944-1977 (Box 114)
  - World Safety Research Institute, 1966-1967; undated (Box 114)
- Series IV: Professional Societies
  - American Astronautical Society, 1969-1976 (Box 114)
  - American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics Meeting and Related Materials, May 1977 (Box 114)
  - International Academy of Astronautics - General, 1968-1980; undated (Box 114)
  - Wings Club, 1972-1976 (Box 115)
  - Women's Advisory Committee on Aviation, 1972 (Box 115)
  - Zonta Club Lecture Materials, 1981 (Box 115)
- Series V: Awards
  - Amelia Earhart Medal, 1957 (Box 115)
  - AVCO-AWA: Helicopter Heroism Award, 1966; undated (Box 115)
  - Congressional Gold Medal, 2010-2012 (Box 115)
  - Lady Grace Hay Drummond Memorial Trophy, 1955 (Box 115)
  - Laura Taber Barbour Air Safety Award, 1964-1981 (Box 115)
  - Smith College Medal, 1969-1971 (Box 115)
  - Wives' Wings, 1962 (Box 115)
  - Miscellaneous-Awards, 1967; undated (Box 115)
- Series VI: Publications
  - Aircraft Fluids Fire Hazard Symposium [symposium coordinated by Heath], 1966 (Box 115)
  - "Air Show", 1949 (Box 115)
  - "Challenge of Air Safety: Is it Safe to Fly?", 1957 (Box 115)
  - Critical Review of the State of Foreign Space Technology, 1978 (Box 115)
  - "Education for Life: The Importance of Safety Education in the Air Age", 1946 (Box 115)
  - Enciclopedia Practica Jackson, 1952-1953 (Box 115)
  - "Flying Club Commandments", 1947 (Box 115)
  - "Flying's Check Pilot, De Haviland and Beaver", 1949 (Box 115)
  - "Flying's Check Pilot Piper Tri-Pacer", 1951 (Box 115)
  - 'Go West, Young Man', Fly North, Young Lady, 1942 (Box 115)
  - "Helio Courier", 1955 (Box 115)
  - "Homemade Racers", 1949 (Box 115)
  - International Space Rescue Symposium, First, 1968-1969 (Box 116)
  - International Space Rescue Symposium, Second, 1969-1971 (Box 116)
  - International Space Rescue Symposium, Third, 1970-1971 (Box 116)
  - International Space Rescue Symposium, Fourth, 1971-1972 (Box 116)
  - International Space Rescue Symposium, Fifth, 1972-1973 (Box 116)
  - National Conference on Aircraft Locator Beacon Implementation, 1968 (Box 116)
  - "Ninety-Niner's Air Meet", 1949 (Box 116)
  - Pilots, Brush Up Those Landings, 1950 (Box 116)
  - "Pilot's Report… Piper Pacer ", 1950 (Box 116)
  - "Space Rescue", 1969; 1971 (Box 117)
  - Space Safety and Rescue, 1979-81 (Box 117)
    General
    [West St.]
  - WASP: "In Their Own Words", An Illustrated History, 2010 (Box 117)
  - WASP: "In Their Own Words", An Illustrated History, 2010 (Box 117)
  - "Wintertime is Snowtime", 1949 (Box 117)
  - Miscellaneous Publications, 1970-1981 (Box 117)
  - Congressional Medal, 2010 (Box OV)
  - Miscellaneous publications regarding flying (Box 117.1)